Guide to the Harry P. Dewey Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Harry P. Dewey Papers
1896-1936
RG 297
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(7 boxes)
The collection documents the professional work of Harry Pinneo Dewey (1861-1937), a Congregational minister in New Hampshire, Brooklyn, and Minneapolis.
Biographical / Historical
Harry Pinneo Dewey was born October 30, 1861, in Toulon, Il. He graduated from Williams College in 1884 and completed the course of study at Andover Theological Seminary in 1887. He was ordained at South Congregational Church in Concord, NH, October 12, 1887, and served that church as minister until 1900. From New Hampshire he moved to New York to become minister of Church of the Pilgrims in Brooklyn. After seven years in Brooklyn, in 1907 Dewey became minister of Plymouth Church in Minneapolis, where he remained until his retirement in 1935.
Dewey was a trustee of several schools and Congregational organizations: Andover Theological Seminary (1907-1937), Home Missionary Society (1908-1909), Carleton College (1911-1937), American Missionary Association (1914-1923), and Straight University (1916-1935). He was also an active member of several other organizations: National Service Commission of Congregational Churches (1917-1919), National Council Commission on Missions (1921-1927), National Council Commission of Twelve for Unification of Congregational Missionary Societies (1923-1927), Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America from National Council (1923-1930).
Dewey died in Babson Park, Fl., April 26, 1937.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School in 2017.
Scope and Contents
The Harry P. Dewey Papers, 1896-1936, document the professional work of Dewey. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: biographical material, travel journal, meditations, addresses, sermons, prayers and miscellaneous literary manuscripts. The bulk of the collection consists of addresses and sermons.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in seven series:
Series I. Biographical material
Series II. Travel Journal
Series III. Meditations
Series IV. Addresses
Series V. Sermons
Series VI. Prayers
Series VII. Miscellaneous Literary Manuscripts
- Biographical Material, Series I
  - Biographical sketch (Box 1)
  - Memorial sermon preached for the Union Church, Boston, 1937 May 16 (Box 1)
  - Photograph, No date (Box 1)
- Travel Journal, Series II
  - Narrative of visit to Lewistown, Illinois (Box 1)
- Meditations, Series III
  - Miscellaneous meditations (Box 1)
- Addresses, Series IV
  - Abraham Lincoln (Box 1)
  - Beginnings and development of the church (Box 1)
  - Biblical classics: IV. The book of Ruth;; V. The prophecy of Hosea (Box 1)
  - Bushnell as an inspirer of men (Box 1)
  - Cherishing the human treasures (Box 1)
  - The cross revealing and testing character (Box 1)
  - Church of the pilgrims (Box 1)
  - God in pursuit (Box 1)
  - Great spiritual leaders and their message to our day: Martin Luther (Box 1)
  - How to read the Bible for guidance, inspiration and comfort (draft) (Box 1)
  - The human and the spiritual in modern poetry (Box 1)
  - Ideals that transform character (draft) (Box 1)
  - Johann Sebastian Bach (Box 1)
  - Life counsels by prophets of literature: I. The coming brotherhood: Lessing's "Nathan the Wise" II. Intellect versus heart: Hawthorne's "Ethan Brand"; Counting the cost of wishes: Balzac's "The Wild Ass's Skin" (Box 1)
  - Life's unsettlements (draft) (Box 1)
  - Life's vocations as a religious discipline: IV. Louis Agassiz, the scientist; V. Daniel Webster, the statesman; VI. Alfred Tennyson, the poet (Box 1)
  - Lodging outside the city (Box 1)
  - The Lord's Supper as the Eucharist (Box 1)
  - Meaning of the communion service (full text and draft) (Box 1)
  - Morals of etiquette (draft) (Box 1)
  - The names of the early Christians (Box 1)
  - [New Year's Eve address] (paraphrased version of address) (Box 1)
  - On being a Christian (Box 1)
  - Opening doors of opportunity (draft) (Box 1)
  - Pledges and foretastes of immortality (Box 1)
  - Privileges of the college experience (Box 1)
  - The Puritan as a preacher (Box 1)
  - Religion in daily life: communion address (Box 1)
  - Shakespeare as a moral and spiritual teacher (Box 1)
  - The soul's upper room (Box 1)
  - Spiritual aims (draft) (Box 1)
  - Spiritual teachings in modern poetry (Box 1)
  - The unsure [illegible word] (Box 1)
  - Ways of showing appreciation (draft) (Box 1)
- Sermons, Series V
  Scope and Contents
  For a full listing of scriptural texts of the sermons, see original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Sermons arranged by text: Genesis - Acts (Box 1)
  - Sermons arranged by text: Romans - III John (Box 2)
  - Sermons arranged chronologically, 1896–1912 (Box 2)
  - Sermons arranged chronologically, 1913–1921 (Box 3)
  - Sermons arranged chronologically, 1922–1927 (Box 4)
  - Sermons arranged chronologically, 1928–1932 (Box 5)
  - Sermons arranged chronologically, 1933–1936 (Box 6)
  - Sermon illustrations, No date (Box 6)
- Prayers, Series VI
  - Undated prayers, No date (Box 6)
  - Prayers arranged chronologically (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous Literary Manuscripts, Series VII
  - Resolution for Williams College trustees re A.C. Chapin and H.J. Brown (Box 7)
  - Invocation at celebration of centenary of Mark Hopkins (Box 7)
  - Impression of autumnal foliage in Berkshires (published in Williams Alumni Review and Boston Evening Transcript ), 1931 (Box 7)
  - Manual, Plymouth Church, Minneapolis, 1941 (Box 7)